<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-01T11:32:24-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tim Maguire</title><subtitle>Tim Maguire&apos;s writing and thoughts on APIs.  Tim has been a Product Manager in the API space since 2018.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Building a Governance Framework</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/01/building-a-governance-framework.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building a Governance Framework" /><published>2024-11-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-11-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/01/building-a-governance-framework</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/01/building-a-governance-framework.html"><![CDATA[<p>In a previous <a href="/2024/09/10/api-product-manager-onboarding-guide.html">post</a>, I outlined a high-level plan for onboarding as a new API Product Manager responsible for an organization’s API governance.  We focused on meeting different stakeholders and gathering the information needed from each team.  As you have begun compiling that data, we’ll make it actionable in this post.</p>

<p>This post provides an example of an API governance framework and demonstrates how it can be applied to an organization.  Keep in mind that a governance framework is a living set of guidelines and standards that evolve as an organization grows and moves along the <a href="/2024/01/25/platform-engineering-maturity-model.html">API Platform Maturity Model</a>. A start-up will have very different requirements from an established enterprise organization in a highly regulated industry such as financial services.  Evaluate your organization against the API Platform Maturity Model and determine which components best fit your organization.</p>

<p>The high-level steps for building an API Governance Framework include:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Defining the Objectives and Goals</li>
  <li>Engaging stakeholders</li>
  <li>Forming a Cross-Functional API Governance Team</li>
  <li>Auditing and Mapping the Existing API Landscape</li>
  <li>Defining and Documenting Governance Policies</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="defining-the-objectives-and-goals">Defining the Objectives and Goals</h2>

<p>When implementing an API governance framework, it is crucial to set clear, measurable goals that align with customers’ needs as well as overall business and technology goals. For example, a goal could be to reduce API implementation lead time by 20% over the next quarter. This specific metric will serve as a focal point for all stakeholders, increasing accountability and driving progress.</p>

<h4 id="developer-experience">Developer Experience</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Objective:</strong> Streamline the development process, reduce friction, and provide clear guidelines for API design, testing, and deployment.</li>
  <li><strong>Goal:</strong> Reduce API implementation lead time by 20% in 3 months.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="api-consumers">API Consumers</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Objective:</strong> Ensure consistent, reliable, and secure APIs for both internal and external consumers.</li>
  <li><strong>Goal:</strong> Enhance API usability and security to improve consumer satisfaction and trust measured by quarterly surveys.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="feedback-loops">Feedback Loops</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Objective:</strong> Establish channels for API developers and consumers to provide feedback on the framework and suggest improvements.</li>
  <li><strong>Goal:</strong> Implement a feedback mechanism that captures and addresses 80% of user suggestions within the quarter.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="documentation--support">Documentation &amp; Support</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Objective:</strong> Provide comprehensive support for developers to understand and quickly implement the framework within their existing workflow.</li>
  <li><strong>Goal:</strong> Achieve a 90% satisfaction rate in developer support services by the end of the quarter.</li>
</ul>

<p>Draft the objectives and goals into an API Governance Mission Statement.  The mission statement should be unique to your organization and contain clear targets specific to the current situation.  It might be a roadmap for moving along the API Platform Maturity Model or your organization might have a mature API program and there are regulatory requirements you must meet.  For instance, the organization might be in a regulated industry such as finance or healthcare and therefore must meet specific regulatory requirements such as HIPAA, FHIR, or GDPR.  Other organizations may have had a security incident and want to put tighter controls around their security and risk management.  The framework could focus more on internal factors such as accountability and transparency by establishing clear ownership and visibility into an organization’s APIs.  Use it as the north star when implementing the framework.</p>

<h2 id="engaging-stakeholders">Engaging stakeholders</h2>

<p>I won’t get into too much detail here, as I’ve outlined how to engage stakeholders in a <a href="/2024/09/10/api-product-manager-onboarding-guide.html">previous post</a>.  However, as you start to think about the framework, socialize your mission statement draft as you meet with stakeholders.  Getting their feedback, ideas, and buy-in early will be critical to the success of the program.  Ensure to use efficient communication channels to streamline engagement in a transparent manner, not all meetings need to be face-to-face.  I have found that setting up a public Slack channel, open meetings, and a wiki page is a good starting point for transparency.  Publish the mission statement, important updates, milestones and meeting recordings to the wiki page.  Then, provide updates to the larger organization through all-hands meetings.</p>

<h2 id="forming-a-governance-team">Forming a Governance Team</h2>

<p>I generally advise against creating ad hoc committees, as they might lead to groupthink or are not a top priority for the team members, however, as you meet with stakeholders, identify enthusiastic partners who will become net promoters of the governance program.  They will be vital in winning over the rest of the organization when rolling out the framework.  I have found that when implementing any sort of change, one third of organization members are usually on board and one third are detractors of the change.  We want to focus on converting the undecided third to the promoter side.  The team should have a representative from each department and each team member should have a specific role and responsibility.  If someone raises objections, listen to them and show empathy, work their feedback into the goals and mission statement.  When I was part of an API governance program, it was some of the most rewarding work I did at the company.  I was also able to meet and learn from team members with whom I don’t necessarily cross paths</p>

<h2 id="documenting-existing-apis">Documenting Existing APIs</h2>

<p>I touched on this briefly in a <a href="/2024/09/10/api-product-manager-onboarding-guide.html">previous post</a>, however as you start to catalog existing APIs quickly review each one for patterns and potential compliance issues. This is not necessarily the time to resolve issues; instead, simply note potential issues such as API versioning, naming conventions, and other elements that may need addressing.  Some of these issues may not be immediately fixable.  This audit provides a foundation as you begin defining governance policies.  In large organizations where APIs grow organically, it’s likely that there will be inconsistencies from API to API.  Rather than judge or question implementation, acknowledge that the team building the API had the best intentions and made the best decision possible with the data they had at the time.  Start to document these issues and as you work with the governance team, you will standardize these APIs.</p>

<h2 id="defining-and-documenting-api-governance-policies">Defining and Documenting API Governance Policies</h2>

<p>Based on stakeholder input and the findings from the API cataloging, start to define a set of policies and standards that will form the foundation of the governance framework.  Some of these may be driven from outside factors such as compliance and regulatory requirements, while others will be driven from internal best practices.  Similar to how an organization has branding guidelines, think of the API as an extension of your organization’s digital brand.  You want a consistent developer experience for all consumers of your APIs and the framework is where you’ll document it.</p>

<p>With the team, identify three pressing issues that can be immediately fixed, document them, and work with the API development teams to put these on their backlogs.  Defining overly rigid policies and standards can stifle innovation and flexibility.  In other words, avoid creating policies for issues that do not exist.  Starting with some foundational, non-intrusive policies will help establish a strong baseline of API quality and consistency without causing disruptions or breaking changes.  Here are some examples where you could start:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>API Documentation Completeness and Accuracy</strong>: Ensure that every REST API is fully documented with an OpenAPI definition.  Include descriptions, examples, error codes, limits and query parameters.  This will immediately reduce support requests and promote better adoption of the APIs.</li>
  <li><strong>Use Consistent Status Codes and Error Handling</strong>: This gets back to my API branding note, having each endpoint return consistent status codes and error messages will provide developers with a predictable implementation.</li>
  <li><strong>Require Consistent Authentication and Authorization, such as OAuth 2.0</strong>: Not only does this improve API security, but makes it easier for developers to understand access requirements leading to a better overall developer experience.</li>
</ul>

<p>Each of these policies can be easily instrumented using tooling such as Spectral and built into a developer’s workflow.  After a while, these policies will become second nature to all API developers within the organization.</p>

<p>I will dig into more specifics and provide examples of governance policies in a future post.  I love to talk about this so let me know what some of your expeeriences have been when implementing a governance framework.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tim Maguire</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In a previous post, I outlined a high-level plan for onboarding as a new API Product Manager responsible for an organization’s API governance. We focused on meeting different stakeholders and gathering the information needed from each team. As you have begun compiling that data, we’ll make it actionable in this post.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Managing Remote Teams</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/24/managing-remote-teams.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Managing Remote Teams" /><published>2024-10-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/24/managing-remote-teams</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/24/managing-remote-teams.html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s a fact of life today — especially in tech — that we’ll be working in a globally distributed workforce. However as teams and companies made the transition from in-office to remote and back or to a hybrid situation, we’ve continued to hold on to our old habits from when we all worked in the office.</p>

<p>I’ve put together some tips and guidelines from my experiences leading globally distributed teams in multiple continents and timezones. Hope these help and would love to hear some of your remote management tips.</p>

<h2 id="managing-teams">Managing Teams</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Clear role definitions</strong> - Ensure that each team member has a clear understanding of their role and responsibilities and how those align to the overall business and team priorities.  This applies for both in person and remote management, however it’s even more vital for remote teams as communication can sometimes be delayed with remote work.  Work their responsibilities into the team’s OKRs and over-communicate their responsibilities to the rest of the team.  My rule of thumb is that when I’m sick of hearing myself say something, the virtual team is starting to get it.</li>
  <li><strong>Respect time zones</strong> - rotate meeting times so no one person is always up early or staying late.  At one point I was managing a team with people based in Europe, Africa, South America and California, with those time differences, there was no good time for everyone for our daily stand ups.  In order to accommodate this, we had a “stand-up” channel in Slack where people would post updates and blockers by a certain time.  We still had a daily call that was optional for team members without blockers.  Another time the dev team I was working with was based in Europe. It was growing old for them to stay late, especially in the summer, so I started getting up early at 5 or 6am before the rest of my family was awake to meet with them for a couple hours.  They were cool with my bed head and PJs as long as they could sign off at a reasonable hour.  After our call, I’d help get my children dressed and off to school, shower, and start my day with a sense of accomplishment.</li>
  <li><strong>Recognize and celebrate different cultures</strong> - spend time to learn about the diverse backgrounds of global teammates and encourage others to share aspects of themselves.  In my last two jobs, I’ve worked with people from Ireland, Poland, Sweden, South Africa, Czech Republic, Italy, Israel, and Germany to name a few.  While I don’t remember everything we worked on or accomplished, what I do treasure is the local colloquialisms and traditions that stay with me to this day.  What’s the Craic?  Braai Day.  Fika. Learning the rules of Rugby.</li>
  <li><strong>Encourage cultural awareness</strong> - provide resources to the team so they understand different communication styles and cultures from around the world.  For instance, Israelis tend to be very direct and can come across as blunt or even rude to someone not expecting it. On the other hand, when working with a team in Sweden, their style was a bit more indirect and tended to look for consensus building when making decisions.</li>
  <li><strong>Celebrate wins</strong> - no matter how trivial they may seem. We created a “Shout-outs” channel in Slack to celebrate wins or publicly thank someone. Then in our weekly team meetings, we would spend 5-10 min to expand on these shout outs.  A little acknowledgement of a small act of kindness can really make someone’s day.</li>
  <li><strong>Encourage a culture of feedback</strong> - This goes for both in-person and remote management and starts with you as the leader. Provide regular constructive time based feedback. I always tried to follow up with a direct report right after an event such as a meeting they ran, demo, or presentation with feedback, what went well, what can be improved.  Ensure it’s constructive and specific.</li>
  <li><strong>Mental health check ins</strong> - Recognize that people working remotely may feel isolated, provide them with support or mental health training focused on the unique challenges of remote work. Check in daily on each team member, even if it’s a simple Slack message such as “How’s things?” or “Do you need anything from me?” Work with your HR department to schedule formalized training or mindfulness sessions.  I scheduled weekly game time during the pandemic where we played Codenames online as a way to unwind.  Just keep in mind that these virtual team building sessions are not for everyone and to respect the decision of those who want to sit it out.</li>
  <li><strong>On-site assistance</strong> - In a hybrid environment, find a local mentor for on-site junior team members.  I had a junior direct report and while I spent a lot of time with her, I wasn’t able to provide her all the mentoring and support she needed to be successful had we been in the office together.  I worked with a peer in the office to provide her with the hands-on mentorship she required to be successful.  Worked both ways as the mentor was able to form a relationship with a colleague 20 years his junior.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="meetings">Meetings</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Regular team check-ins</strong> - Schedule a weekly team wide check-in to discuss progress, challenges, and team morale. Review the team’s progress toward quarterly or annual OKRs, progress on projects with RYG status with asks for help, blocker identification, and lastly a general team vibe check in. I originally got the idea of team morale from reviewing my children’s remote schooling slides, everyday, they would have to report on their mood with three emojis.  A simple yet effective means to track the team morale and furthermore, report on this just as closely as big deliverables and set up goals around team morale.</li>
  <li><strong>Confirm meeting agenda</strong> - spend the first 3-5 min of every meeting confirming the agenda in order to assure everyone is in the right place. There may be some brainstorming meetings that lack rigid structure, if that’s the case, note it at the start of the meeting.</li>
  <li>**Use video on calls - **strongly encourage video when necessary, especially in 1on1s, team meetings, or smaller meetings especially as the team is growing in order to build rapport.  I have found that this really helps build team rapport and chemistry, especially for a new or growing team.  On the flip side, recognize that video fatigue is real and some people might prefer to take a break from video, therefore respect the decision of those on larger calls with maybe more than ten people,</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="one-on-ones">One-on-ones</h2>

<p>This section is evergreen advice for remote, hybrid, and in-person work environments and should be gospel for all managers, no matter their level or years of experience.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Schedule weekly 1on1s with every direct report</strong>. Bi-weekly 1on1s with second level reports. These times are sacred and keep these meetings on the books at all costs. Last minute cancellations can send an employee spinning.  I would always get into my own head when a manager canceled a one on one at the last minute.</li>
  <li><strong>Be consistent</strong> - Start every 1on1 with the same question, I like “What’s the most important thing right now?” or “How’s it going?”  The answer does not always have to be work related, an employee’s family member could be sick and that’s the most important thing to them right now.  This helps pick up on patterns as well.  I used to start every 1on1 with “How’s it going?” and one direct report who answered “fine” every week for several months, then one day she sighed and said “OK.”  This signaled something was off, while it wasn’t exactly work related, we were able to discuss in vague terms and she took some personal days to handle some things.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="communication">Communication</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Use asynchronous communications</strong> as much as possible - Slack, Email.  Patience is the key, you should expect to wait 24 hours for a reply for non-urgent matters. For items that may seem urgent, I have found that just typing out the question would force me to look at a problem in a new way and I’ll find an answer.</li>
  <li><strong>Use the send later feature</strong> in Slack or email to be mindful of different time zones. On the flip side, use do not disturb settings in Slack and your phone to limit off hours notifications.  Respect your co-workers time outside of regular business hours.  There was once I received a Slack message after 8pm and rather than unwinding from the day and spending time with my family, I’d open my laptop and next thing I’d know it’d be several hours later, way past my bedtime and I’d be set up for failure the following day.</li>
  <li><strong>Disseminate Slack etiquette</strong>. This tends to differ from company to company so when new people join an organization they’ll rely on their previous organization’s Slack culture. Some examples that have worked for me:
    <ul>
      <li>Limit private DMs</li>
      <li>Make everything public, channels are free, use them. Create a “tmp-project” channel for a short lived project.</li>
      <li>Use threads for deep dives/rat holes</li>
      <li>Set up a public “ask-me” or “ask-tim” channel for people to drop in and ask random questions. This keeps communications public and builds up a knowledge base</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Create a strong culture of documentation</strong> – Use a wiki, there are plenty of options to use, don’t get hung up looking for the perfect solution.  The simplest format I’ve used is just a Google Doc with ongoing notes and decisions for the team. It was crude but effective for a team of three people.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Tim Maguire</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s a fact of life today — especially in tech — that we’ll be working in a globally distributed workforce. However as teams and companies made the transition from in-office to remote and back or to a hybrid situation, we’ve continued to hold on to our old habits from when we all worked in the office.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">API Futures | API Product Manager Onboarding Guide</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/10/api-product-manager-onboarding-guide.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="API Futures | API Product Manager Onboarding Guide" /><published>2024-09-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-09-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/10/api-product-manager-onboarding-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/10/api-product-manager-onboarding-guide.html"><![CDATA[<p>Congratulations on your new role as an API Product Manager! It’s an exciting opportunity to shape an organization’s API strategy and governance. Once the dopamine of the LinkedIn likes and congratulations reactions wear off, it’s time to dive into the essentials of your role. Here’s a framework to help you thoughtfully onboard and make an impact.</p>

<h3 id="onboarding-framework-for-api-product-managers"><strong>Onboarding Framework for API Product Managers</strong></h3>

<p>Many new Product Managers feel the urge to prove their value quickly by delivering new features within the first 30 days. However, it’s crucial to first understand your organization’s unique landscape before diving into the backlog. Here’s a structured approach to guide your first 30-60 days, focusing on understanding the existing environment and laying a solid foundation before building your roadmap.</p>

<h4 id="1-understand-the-existing-api-landscape"><strong>1. Understand the Existing API Landscape</strong></h4>

<p>Start by meeting key stakeholders to identify and catalog all existing APIs, along with their owners, consumers, and the purpose of each service. If you’re a visual thinker like me, consider mapping these APIs onto a workflow digram and organizational chart. This exercise will give you a holistic view of the API ecosystem, enabling you to understand interdependencies and identify potential gaps or overlaps.</p>

<h4 id="2-develop-metrics"><strong>2. Develop Metrics</strong></h4>

<p>Collaborate with teams to establish Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) or Service Level Objectives (SLOs) for API performance and governance. Key metrics might include uptime, latency, error rates, compliance adherence, and security incidents. Even if it’s just the first step, measuring these data points will provide invaluable insights into where improvements are needed.</p>

<h4 id="3-establish-a-governance-framework"><strong>3. Establish a Governance Framework</strong></h4>

<p>Work with stakeholders to document and socialize a governance framework that includes best API design, security, and lifecycle management practices. Ensure all relevant teams are involved in crafting this framework to foster buy-in and ensure that it’s practical and enforceable. If no framework exists, start small and build on it incrementally.</p>

<h4 id="4-create-a-centralized-api-catalog"><strong>4. Create a Centralized API Catalog</strong></h4>

<p>Develop a business-focused API catalog that includes comprehensive documentation, use cases, getting-started guides, sample code, SDKs, and versioning information. Organize it with non-technical users in mind to ensure that it’s accessible to everyone within the organization.</p>

<h3 id="key-meetings-in-your-first-30-days"><strong>Key Meetings in Your First 30 Days</strong></h3>

<p>Your first 30 days should be focused on meeting with various stakeholders across the organization. The insights you gather will be crucial for shaping your API strategy. Key stakeholders include:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Engineering Teams:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Goal: Understand the API architecture, technical challenges, and development processes.</li>
      <li>Gather details on existing APIs, their business value, versioning and deprecation strategies, and the development lifecycle. Assess the tools and processes used for API development, testing, monitoring, and documentation.</li>
      <li>Discuss any security or compliance requirements (e.g., HIPAA, GDPR) and how these are addressed.</li>
      <li>Identify challenges related to API security, scalability, and performance, reviewing post-mortems from recent outages or incidents to gain insights.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>API Consumers (e.g., Business Unit Leaders):</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Goal: Understand how existing APIs impact their workflows.</li>
      <li>Map their workflows to specific APIs and identify any critical gaps. Look for examples where manual workarounds are used (e.g., extracting data to spreadsheets) as these indicate areas for improvement.</li>
      <li>Assess the adequacy of API documentation, ensuring it meets the needs of both technical and non-technical users.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Legal and Compliance Teams:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Goal: Ensure APIs comply with industry standards and regulations.</li>
      <li>Gather specific regulatory requirements that your APIs must adhere to and incorporate these into your governance framework. Work closely with the security team to integrate proper security standards into the API lifecycle.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Other Product Managers:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Goal: Gain insights into how they manage their API-related backlogs and align with business goals.</li>
      <li>Learn about their processes for gathering user feedback, managing user personas, and handling API versioning and deprecation.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Third Parties (e.g., Vendors, Customers):</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Goal: Gather external feedback to improve API usability.</li>
      <li>Understand their key use cases, onboarding experiences, and the challenges they face when using your APIs. This feedback is crucial for identifying areas of improvement and building stronger external relationships.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="quick-wins-in-your-first-60-days"><strong>Quick Wins in Your First 60 Days</strong></h3>

<p>As you gather information, look for opportunities to deliver quick wins that don’t require heavy engineering effort. These could include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Improving or updating API documentation.</li>
  <li>Writing getting started guides or creating sample code.</li>
  <li>Streamlining onboarding processes for new developers or third parties.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="next-steps"><strong>Next Steps</strong></h3>

<p>In my next post, I’ll discuss how to use the feedback you’ve gathered to build a governance framework and integrate it into the development workflow to ensure compliance and efficiency.</p>

<p>By following this framework, you’ll set yourself up for success, laying the groundwork for effective API management and governance within your organization.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tim Maguire</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Congratulations on your new role as an API Product Manager! It’s an exciting opportunity to shape an organization’s API strategy and governance. Once the dopamine of the LinkedIn likes and congratulations reactions wear off, it’s time to dive into the essentials of your role. Here’s a framework to help you thoughtfully onboard and make an impact.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">API Futures | Building the Platform Engineering MVP</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/07/16/building-the-platform-engineering-mvp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="API Futures | Building the Platform Engineering MVP" /><published>2024-07-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-07-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/07/16/building-the-platform-engineering-mvp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/07/16/building-the-platform-engineering-mvp.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the thrid post in my Platform Engineering Paves the Path for API Management and Governance series.  In the <a href="/2024/01/09/api-futures-platform-engineering.html">first post</a>, I provided a high-level overview of Platform Engineering and how it can help API governance.  In my <a href="/2024/01/25/platform-engineering-maturity-model.html">second post</a>, I shared a Platform Engineering Maturity Model.  This post focuses on how a Platform Product Manager can get started building a Platform within an organization.</p>

<h2 id="just-build-an-mvp">Just Build an MVP</h2>

<p>Many articles I have read that make the case for Platform Engineering always contain a “Build an MVP” or TVP - “Thinnest Viable Platform” step.  While well-intentioned, I’ve always struggled with exactly what should go into that MVP.  Do you start by building CI/CD pipelines? Layering in monitoring and observability functionality? Are there security issues such as access control to address?  Any of these capabilities and countless others would make for a viable prototype of your platform.  There are so many options and paths to go down, just picking one could be the hardest step.  Additionally, suppose the Platform Product Manager polled each developer or executive on what functionality they’d want to see in a Platform. There’d be just as many opinions on what to include and we’d be stuck in an analysis paralysis loop.  We need to find the one capability that will move the needle for the larger organization as a whole and aligns with the needs of both development and executive teams.</p>

<h3 id="align-with-development-teams">Align with Development Teams</h3>

<p>As a product leader, it’s our responsibility to work with developers to understand their key pain points and the things holding them back.  Many times, these aren’t “blockers” meaning they don’t have a workaround, but really “anchors.”  Developers can still get their job done, however the anchor is adding friction and holding them back.</p>

<p>In order to gather qualitative data from the teams, the platform product manager not only needs to be embedded within the platform development team but the rest development teams across the organization.  Attend their sprint demos to get an understanding of what they are working on, their accomplishments, and things that may be holding them back.  Review their retrospectives, keying in on themes for improvements.  Additionally, build up personal connections with other developers and developer team leaders.  These relationships will help uncover some of their biggest pain points without the political sugarcoating.</p>

<p>Quantitative data comes from reviewing bug reports, monthly or quarterly say/do metrics, and for more mature organizations, DORA metrics.</p>

<h3 id="developing-executive-allies">Developing Executive Allies</h3>

<p>Product and Engineering leaders must recognize executives’ broad focus and competing priorities. A typical mistake product leaders make is focusing too much on their own needs, thinking, “If I’m successful, my executive team will be successful.”  This is better framed as “What are the executive’s goals, and how can I best support them?”</p>

<p>Executives’ context switches throughout the day, and one of the first mistakes you can make is assuming that your ask is their most pressing need.  Execs have sales, product, HR, fundraising, and finances on their mind every day, so there’s not enough room to consider the nuances of a platform engineering team and how it’ll help the overall API program.</p>

<p>With that in mind, it’s best to understand what’s most important to the executive team.  Are they concerned about software quality?  Time to market?  Developer productivity?  Reducing costs?  Take the time to understand what keeps the executives up at night regarding software delivery.</p>

<h3 id="building-the-mvp">Building the MVP</h3>

<p>Once we have feedback and data from developers and executives, we are ready to build the first iteration of our platform.  I like to gather feedback on stickies and group them by category, looking for clusters of pain points and address these first.  Below are some common groupings that a platform engineering team will need to address along with common solutions and outcomes for each category.  This framework will help build your platform story and set the team’s purpose and charter toward the platform MVP.</p>

<p>Now it’s time to build software, build a platform proof of concept over a couple sprints to show progress honing in on your key metrics and how they align to the organization’s needs.  Gather the internal feedback and continue to iterate.  This POC will prove your platform story and that the platform engineering team will lift the capabilities of the entire development team.</p>

<table>
  <tr>
   <th>Type
   </th>
   <th>Executive Concern
   </th>
   <th>Development Team Concern
   </th>
   <th>Solution
   </th>
   <th>Outcomes
   </th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <td>Security and Compliance
   </td>
   <td>Data security, regulatory compliance
   </td>
   <td>Security vulnerabilities, compliance
   </td>
   <td>Adding automated tooling for vulnerability scanning, better access controls, and automated compliance checks
   </td>
   <td>Protects sensitive data, ensures regulatory compliance, and enhances your security posture
   </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <td>Customer Satisfaction
   </td>
   <td>User experience, customer feedback
   </td>
   <td>Bug tracking &amp; resolution, rapid feedback loops
   </td>
   <td>Add monitoring and logging systems to track performance, errors, and user behavior.  Integrate feedback tools
   </td>
   <td>Transparency into system health, allows for quick issue identification and resolution, and gathers insights into improvement
   </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <td>Time to Market
   </td>
   <td>Speed of delivery, release frequency
   </td>
   <td>Release management and deployment automation.
   </td>
   <td>Implement CI/CD pipelines, automated testing, and deployment tools
   </td>
   <td>Speeds the release cycle, reduces manual errors, and ensures consistent deployment practices
   </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <td>Quality and Reliability
   </td>
   <td>Defect rates, system uptime and availability
   </td>
   <td>Code quality, testing and QA coverage
   </td>
   <td>Provide tools for automated testing, static code analysis, and continuous monitoring
   </td>
   <td>Improves code quality, reducing defect rate, catches bugs early, and ensures adherence to coding standards
   </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <td>Scalability and Flexibility
   </td>
   <td>Scalability, flexibility
   </td>
   <td>Performance, optimization, scalability
   </td>
   <td>Provide infrastructure that can scale automatically based on demand and tools to monitor application performance
   </td>
   <td>Ensures the application can handle increasing loads and maintains optimal performance
   </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <td>Innovation and Competitive Edge
   </td>
   <td>Innovation rate, market position
   </td>
   <td>Rapid feedback loop, bug tracking
   </td>
   <td>Provide feature flagging tools, A/B testing, and quick rollback mechanisms to enable controlled rollouts and experimentation
   </td>
   <td>Allows for safe deployment of new features, rapid iteration based on user feedback, and data-driven decision-making
   </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <td>Team productivity and morale
   </td>
   <td>Developer productivity, employee satisfaction
   </td>
   <td>Collaboration and communication, knowledge sharing
   </td>
   <td>Integration and collaboration platforms and maintain centralized documentation
   </td>
   <td>Facilitates better communication, knowledge sharing, and alignment among team members.
   </td>
  </tr>
</table>]]></content><author><name>Tim Maguire</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the thrid post in my Platform Engineering Paves the Path for API Management and Governance series. In the first post, I provided a high-level overview of Platform Engineering and how it can help API governance. In my second post, I shared a Platform Engineering Maturity Model. This post focuses on how a Platform Product Manager can get started building a Platform within an organization.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">API Futures | Platform Engineering Maturity Model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/25/platform-engineering-maturity-model.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="API Futures | Platform Engineering Maturity Model" /><published>2024-01-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/01/25/platform-engineering-maturity-model</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/25/platform-engineering-maturity-model.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the second post in my Platform Engineering Paves the Path for API Management and Governance series.  In the <a href="/2024/01/09/api-futures-platform-engineering.html">first post</a>, I provided a high-level overview of Platform Engineering and how it can help API governance.  In this post, we’ll dive into a Platform Engineering Maturity Model.</p>

<p>Organizations use a maturity model framework to assess and measure the capabilities of a process or program to gauge where they are today and plot a course or roadmap of where they want to go by identifying specific areas in which to invest.  A traditional maturity model consists of four phases: Initial, Managed, Defined, and Optimizing.</p>

<table>
  <tr>
   <th>Phase
   </th>
   <th>Description
   </th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <td>0 - Initial
   </td>
   <td>Ad hoc, unpredictable
   </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <td>1 - Managed
   </td>
   <td>Defined process in some areas
   </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <td>2 - Defined
   </td>
   <td>Defined process for organization, proactive
   </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <td>3 - Optimizing
   </td>
   <td>Processes are measured, controlled, and focus on improvement
   </td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>Let’s look at these phases within the context of a platform engineering team.</p>

<h3 id="phase-0---initial-or-pure-chaos">Phase 0 - Initial or Pure Chaos.</h3>

<p>Developers might be productive in pockets, but it’s inconsistent and unpredictable.  Individual teams within the organization may have different processes and rigor regarding software development and delivery.</p>

<p>Teams don’t have great insights into how the overall system performs; triaging and resolving system outages is more reactionary.  After an incident, the team documents the root cause. However, they tend to put the solution on an ambiguous backlog with no apparent owner rather than fixing it immediately before they move to the next problem.</p>

<p>Because there is no process, API designs – if there are any – become inconsistent from API to API and team to team.  Developers implement interfaces differently from team to team and even from API to API within the same team.  When designing an API, a team might spend excessive effort components that could be reusable, such as pagination.  Teams might reimplement an existing API slightly differently because there is a lack of API documentation and discovery.</p>

<p>Here are some critical steps an organization can take to move up to the Developing phase:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Identify a Platform Team – ideally, this should be a team of developers focused solely on the platform and improving the development experience.</li>
  <li>Work with Stakeholders to identify priorities and concerns – the platform team should interview nearly every developer and product development leader to understand the key things keeping them up at night.</li>
  <li>Prioritize and Build a Thinnest Viable Product (TVP) – based on the feedback, identify the critical problems to solve and map them to outcomes.  This includes defining success criteria in the form of metrics.</li>
  <li>Socialize outcomes – it’s crucial to celebrate wins and share the TVP and success outcomes with the rest of the organization.  This will build credibility within the organization, which is needed for later phases.</li>
</ul>

<p>Example:  Developers start grumbling about their tooling or a process within the organization.  A platform team member interviews developers to understand their pain points, how many developers this impacts, and the pain frequency.  With this quantifiable data, the platform team can work on solving these pain points as the first iteration of the TVP, paving their path to the next phase - Managed.</p>

<h3 id="phase-1---managed-or-controlled-chaos">Phase 1 - Managed or Controlled Chaos</h3>

<p>The TVP is in place, and a platform team exists.  The TVP might vary from a simple wiki with some process documentation to a list of identified services and their documentation.  The platform team owns the ambiguous backlog from phase 0. However, there isn’t a clear roadmap or plan to execute on the roadmap.  It can be best described as a list of divergent technical debt issues to solve.</p>

<p>A delicate balance must be struck here as the adoption of the TVP is limited to a small segment of teams or use cases.  Some teams might view this as a success, while others that don’t yet leverage the benefits might see the platform team as overhead until their use cases are covered.  The platform team will start introducing more tooling to the TVP (at this point, we can retire the term) to cover these additional use cases, bringing more teams on board the platform.</p>

<p>In terms of an API program, organizations at this phase will become more formalized in their API design and development processes.  The platform team introduces internal or third-party tooling to the ecosystem to support API use cases.  The platform provides OpenAPI templates, scaffolding, and documented standards to jump-start API design, development, and testing.</p>

<p>Moving from this phase to the Defined phase requires a push-to-pull paradigm shift within an organization, meaning developers will start looking to the platform team to solve many of their problems.  Key steps to move to the next phase include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Build out the Platform Team – consider adding product managers, solution architects, and evangelists.</li>
  <li>Use case expansion – identify bottlenecks that can be automated, such as CI/CD.</li>
  <li>Systematic feedback – regular surveys and conversations rolled into the roadmap.</li>
  <li>Transparent roadmap – the platform product manager must share feedback and the roadmap with the rest of the development team and key stakeholders.</li>
  <li>Software delivery metrics – define, measure, and report on software delivery performance using DORA metrics.</li>
</ul>

<p>Example:  The platform team wants to capture more data automatically, for instance, lead time, so they instrument the build process.  They document and provide scripts for all the development teams to start collecting this data.  Two issues arise: 1) differences in builds from team to team prevent the scripts from being fully adopted, and 2) there are critical steps in the lead time process – PR reviews – that are not being fully calculated in this metric.  As the platform team looks to address these issues, they will start the journey to the next phase – Defined.</p>

<h3 id="phase-2--defined-or-scaling-beyond-the-chaos">Phase 2 – Defined or Scaling Beyond the Chaos</h3>

<p>There is no more chaos at this phase, and the platform begins to scale across the organization.  The organization manages the platform like its external-facing products – staffed with an entire product team, published roadmap, and KPIs regularly reported to the organization along with standard financial metrics.</p>

<p>Development teams choose to use the platform’s capabilities because of its value and less because of organizational mandates.  Developers quickly spin up preconfigured environments and infrastructure based on their needs, knowing these common toolsets are uniform across the organization.  Updates made to test environments by the platform team are pulled into the new environments.</p>

<p>For APIs, governance and standards are in place for common naming conventions, interfaces, and patterns.  Guardrails are automated and built into a developer workflow.  Developers only need to think about the capabilities of their APIs rather than the overall design, as much of the boilerplate definition is already there.</p>

<p>Steps to the final phase, Optimizing:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Platform adoption – internal and external teams besides engineering begin to leverage the platform.</li>
  <li>Organizational buy-in – DORA metrics become the organization’s everyday language and are referenced just as financial metrics.</li>
  <li>Decentralized platform ownership – the platform team still exists; however, additional capabilities are built and contributed back to the platform for organizational-wide adoption.</li>
</ul>

<p>Example: Even with OpenAPI templates, developer teams need help to design APIs as much of their cognitive load is spent learning the intricacies of OpenAPI and ensuring their API designs meet the organizational standards.  The platform team builds tooling that reduces the designer’s exposure to OpenAPI and automates the design to adhere to the organization’s API standards.  Now, API designers only need to think about the use cases of the API and not additional tooling such as linters.  As more and more API designers use this tooling across the organization, the path is paved to move to Phase 3 - Optimizing.</p>

<h3 id="phase-3---optimizing-or-the-holy-grail">Phase 3 - Optimizing or “The Holy Grail”</h3>

<p>In the most mature phase, Optimizing, the platform becomes part of the larger development ecosystem and is a crucial differentiator for the organization.  Note the “-ing” at this phase; organizations never really leave this phase as they continue to evolve and iterate on their platform as new products and technical capabilities are introduced.</p>

<p>Organizations in this phase provide self-service capabilities for developers. This gives the development team the autonomy to make decisions while providing the required organizational guardrails – security, compliance, costs, and standards.  This combination enables developers to focus on delivering innovation and business value as quickly as possible.</p>

<p>The platform is instrumented for constant feedback and monitoring – the platform team understand the usage patterns and can quickly identify points of friction.  It’s these friction points that continue to evolve and make the platform more robust for the development teams.  This efficiency is realized in delightful experiences beyond ones just built for developers.  For instance, onboarding new users, customers, or partners – tasks that once took heroics and weeks or months of time – are now be automated with a push of a button.</p>

<hr />

<p>My next post will focus on getting executive buy-in for a Platform Engineering effort.  This is the most critical piece in this series, as tech is always the easy part, but getting buy-in and funding are the biggest challenges.</p>

<p>Thank you for reading this far. I would love to hear from you about your experiences and where you think your organization sits on the maturity model. I would also like to discuss how you can move your organization forward.  What are some platform success stories? Failures?  My contact information is in the footer.</p>

<hr />

<blockquote>
  <p><em>This post is part of <a href="https://matthewreinbold.github.io/APIFutures/index.html">APIFutures</a>, a community-led, collaborative effort to identify the top challenges and opportunities facing the API economy in 2024. For other perspectives, read the articles by different authors listed <a href="https://matthewreinbold.github.io/APIFutures/index.html">here</a>.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="/">Home</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Tim Maguire</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the second post in my Platform Engineering Paves the Path for API Management and Governance series. In the first post, I provided a high-level overview of Platform Engineering and how it can help API governance. In this post, we’ll dive into a Platform Engineering Maturity Model.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">API Futures | Platform Engineering Paves the Path for API Management and Governance</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/09/api-futures-platform-engineering.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="API Futures | Platform Engineering Paves the Path for API Management and Governance" /><published>2024-01-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/01/09/api-futures-platform-engineering</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/09/api-futures-platform-engineering.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p><em>When brainstorming topics for the <a href="https://matthewreinbold.github.io/APIFutures/index.html">APIFutures</a> initiative, one theme that stood out was Platform Engineering and its benefits to an organization.  I kept reading and listening to podcasts on how Platform Engineering and DORA metrics streamline software development and delivery.  As I took notes and learned more about this topic, I decided to roll this into the API Futures project and start a series on how Platform Engineering streamlines API management and governance.  This first post introduces the problems a Platform Engineering team can solve and provides a sneak peek of the series.  Hope you enjoy this post and return for the rest of the series. I look forward to feedback to keep the discussion going.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="/assets/img/PartAPIFutures.png" alt="Part of APIFutures" title="APIFutures" /></p>

<p>APIs are the building blocks of software.  They facilitate communication and data exchange between various software applications and services and are critical to any organization. However, as organizations create more APIs to meet their business needs, their API ecosystems become complex and challenging to manage. This leads to inconsistent APIs, slower and more complex API development processes, and increases the risk of security flaws in your APIs.  Organizations need a consistent API design and development process to combat this.  It’s vital to reign in this API sprawl, where APIs grow organically with different implementations. This is where a Platform Engineering program can help drive governance and oversight in the API development process.</p>

<p>Building a Platform Engineering program requires strategic practices and patterns to streamline enterprise software delivery.  These initiatives originated at companies like Google and Netflix, blessed with enormous developer teams.  There, the Platform Engineering (PE) team would provide tools, workflows, and best practices to internal developers.  This enabled developers to focus on building applications and APIs that deliver direct business value without worrying about managing infrastructure, Kubernetes (K8s) configurations, or knowing which cloud to deploy to.</p>

<p>Developers like solving hard problems. However, routine tasks such as finding documentation and knowing if that documentation is up to date or figuring out the proper configuration of a K8s cluster should not be complex problems. When these tasks become difficult, developer fatigue and burnout lead to lower-quality APIs, inefficient processes, employee churn, and security exposure. We aim to improve the developer experience by providing the tools developers need to reduce this friction and the additional cognitive load on the developer.</p>

<p>This practice is sometimes called a Paved Path, meaning the platform engineering team provides a paved path for developers to deliver business value quickly.  <a href="https://www.gartner.com/en/articles/what-is-platform-engineering">Gartner</a> forecasts that 80% of software organizations will have a platform team by 2026. According to <a href="https://www.puppet.com/resources/state-of-platform-engineering">Puppet</a>, organizations that have already instituted a platform have seen an increase of 68% in software delivery.  I like envisioning software releases as boring non-events; they just happen, and no one is paged; a platform team can help achieve this.</p>

<p>A well-designed platform focuses on four fundamental principles:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Self-Service Empowerment</li>
  <li>Developer Experience (DX)</li>
  <li>Product Mindset</li>
  <li>Constant monitoring and feedback</li>
</ul>

<p>However, setting up an API platform comes with its challenges. we must:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Balance openness and security to ensure security standards are met with minimal friction</li>
  <li>Ensure scalability to accommodate increasing API usage while versioning APIs and backward compatibility</li>
  <li>Leverage API governance and documentation to maintain consistency across APIs</li>
</ul>

<p>This series aims to provide a detailed exploration of API Platform Engineering. Along the way, we’ll:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Build an API Platform Maturity Model, which can be used to benchmark your organization</li>
  <li>Getting started on the platform engineering journey, starting with building the business case</li>
  <li>Review team topologies</li>
  <li>Develop and prioritize a roadmap for implementation,</li>
  <li>Finish with monitoring and gathering feedback for future iterations.</li>
  <li>Review case studies of successful and unsuccessful implementations</li>
</ul>

<p>By the end of this series, my goal is that you understand what goes into building a thriving platform team, providing valuable insights into its components, best practices, and the path to successful implementation, paving the way for a best-in-class API program.</p>

<p>Thanks for reading.  I would love to hear from you if you have any feedback.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>This post is part of <a href="https://matthewreinbold.github.io/APIFutures/index.html">APIFutures</a>, a community-led, collaborative effort to identify the top challenges and opportunities facing the API economy in 2024. For other perspectives, read the articles by different authors listed <a href="https://matthewreinbold.github.io/APIFutures/index.html">here</a>.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="/">Home</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When brainstorming topics for the APIFutures initiative, one theme that stood out was Platform Engineering and its benefits to an organization. I kept reading and listening to podcasts on how Platform Engineering and DORA metrics streamline software development and delivery. As I took notes and learned more about this topic, I decided to roll this into the API Futures project and start a series on how Platform Engineering streamlines API management and governance. This first post introduces the problems a Platform Engineering team can solve and provides a sneak peek of the series. Hope you enjoy this post and return for the rest of the series. I look forward to feedback to keep the discussion going.]]></summary></entry></feed>